阿弥陀佛
Buddha be praised
辛苦，辛苦
You did a great job
请坐
have a seat
谢谢
thanks
请
please
今天晚上的十八罗汉收大鹏  你们唱得可真是精彩
that was a great performance tonight
你过奖了
thank you
现在先给你们一点酬金
here are your fees
全部都在这儿，请点收
as we agreed
还有，这是点小意思，不成敬意
here's an extra bonus
谢谢
thank you
别客气
don't mention it
我们这里实在太偏僻了  好多年来都没有请过班子来了
we're out in the wilderness
你们的班子肯到我们这儿来唱  你们真是给面子
it's so nice of you to come
你太客气了
it's our pleasure
早点睡了
it's late
我不打扰你们了 ，告辞
I'll be leaving now
谢谢
good night
请留步
不远送了
watch your steps
张大哥，要不要沏点水？
You want some tea, Mr. chiang?
不用了 ，你早点睡吧
No, thanks
我明天一早还得赶路呢
you'd better go to bed
明儿见
see you tomorrow
好， 明天见
good night
难道昨天晚上…
Those were ghosts
这件事你觉得怪不怪？
Does this seem strange to you?
张大叔，这样说起来  你大概常常遇见鬼了
So you run into ghosts often
你才常见鬼呐
that's not nice
大叔说了这么多  你也不知道忌讳，还在乱说
ghosts should not be joked about
我们戏班里的人常常装神弄鬼扮小人
in our business of Chinese opera
免不了会遇到些邪门怪道的事
we play ghosts very often
所以有些忌讳一定要记住
we should respect them
对不起，我们路经贵地打扰了
forgive us if we disturbed you
走吧，小心点
watch out for things
张大叔，你怎么这么迷信呀？
you're that superstitious, uncle chiang?
我见过的怪事太多了 ，我不得不相信
I grew up with those things
我就不相信
I don't believe in ghosts
我知道这次不是鬼， 是你
that wasn't done by a ghost
谁叫你打我的？
you hit me first
这叫自讨苦吃
you deserved it
别开玩笑了 ，走吧
stop fooling around
你们后辈小伙子脾气太坏了
you newcomers have such bad temper
吵什么吵？  你的主人有人抬我是两条腿走路
your master travels first class, we have to walk
再吵就宰了你
shut up or I'll kill you
我来拿吧
I'll get it
不用 ，我是开玩笑
I was only kidding
到啦
we're here
你睡这儿
That's your bed
挑剩的给我
it's the worst
换张床睡好不好？
Can we change beds?
先到先得，没得商量
No way
我怕蚊子咬
I hate mosquitoes
我还怕耗子呢
I hate rats
等你挑大梁的时候，一个人睡单人房
you're not a big star
就不会跟我窝在一块儿了
don't try to be fussy
免崽子呀，别噜苏了
now leave me alone
真的没得商量？
is that it?
没得商量
Yes
夕阳西照 ，月影东流
The moon will shine over here
眨包标，你真行，我佩服你
piao, you're doomed
阿贵，你这话是什么意思？
what does that mean?
没有，没什么意思
Whatever it means
你这样乱说， 是不吉利的
don't try to scare me
我是依书直说呀
I'm just telling the facts
依书？依什么书呀？
what facts?
赖布衣的风水指南，你看过没有？
Have you read the night guide?
你的床是三煞位
yours is doomed
不过你可以不理这些忌讳  当它没事一样
I'd better not say anymore
有没有法子可以挡住这些煞气呀？
what should I do then?
譬方挂个八卦
Anything at all?
养缸金鱼呢？
Tell me please
这个窗的阳光刚好照着你的床上
light from the window shines on your bed
你知不知道这叫什么？ 不知道
- do you know what that means? - No
这叫虎落平阳被犬欺
you may run into ghosts
你睡在床底下或者可以避一避
you'd better sleep under the bed
我去整理床啦
I'm going to bed
睡在床底下？这怎么睡呀？
I'm scared
贵哥，你是属什么的？
Kuei, what year were you born?
相书上是这么说
that's what they say
贵哥，跟我换一张床好不好呀？
can you change beds with me?
换床？不行，不可以
Of course not
你命大罩得住，拜托拜托
please, I'll owe you one
太麻烦了 ，又要把东西搬过去
I'm too tired
还要帮你把床也擦干净
I've dirtied this bed already
不用不用 ，床我自己擦， 东西我帮你拿
don't worry, I'll take care of everything
贵哥，帮帮忙
please help me out
算了 ，算了
alright
刚才你困过我的床没有？
did you sleep on that bed?
我只是躺了一会儿
For just a few seconds
躺过？放些利是钱在床底下
you'd better place a red packet there
不然的话，恶运会跟着你
or the ghosts won't be pleased
想救都救不了
got it?
谢啦
Yes
贵哥，又找到凯子啦？
you conned him
别管闭事呀
stay out of it
或者你说得对呀  可能真的是三煞位也说不定
maybe the bed is really doomed
百无禁忌
nonsense
贵哥，睡在这张床是舒服得多了
this bed is far more comfortable
干什么？ 人有三急
- What's up? - Call of nature
真是懒人屎尿多
this time of the night?
喂， 陪我一块儿去好吗？
I'm scared to go alone
你怎么那么胆小呀
you're such a coward
又不是叫你去抢东西，去尿尿嘛
what's there to be afraid of?
你有没有听说过尿尿一块尿  不然会烂掉
Ghosts, devils, monsters
好了 ，我陪你好了 ，你别噜苏了
alright, I'll go with you
尿尿也不敢
so gutless
对不起呀大哥，请让一让呀
excuse me please
你是怎么搞的？  又要我陪你又要我让一让
I thought you wanted me here
不是我是跟他们说一声
I was talking to them
跟他们？
them?
这种事你也会信？
You believe in ghosts
不是
yes
不是？
stupid
那边有个骨坛，我就尿给你看看
I'll urinate over that grave
小心撞邪呀
don't do that
算你运气不好了 ，想避也避不开
sorry about that, my friend
味道好不好呀？
how did that taste?
有点咸
Terrible
喂喂喂，快走吧
we'd better run
干什么？ 有鬼呀
- why? - Ghosts
你说什么有点咸呀？
why did you say terrible?
你问味道好不好呀 没有
- You asked me how did it taste - I didn't
没有？ 没有
- really? - Really
鬼呀
Ghosts
干什么？
What's up?
吓你呀
Having fun
整天拿点假的东西来吓人  就算是真的我也不一定害伯
I'm not afraid of ghosts
贵哥，怎么你常常撞鬼的？
do you run into ghosts often?
不是撞， 是见
Yes
见？你怎么会见鬼的？
how can you tell?
因为我有一双眼
I have two eyes
废话，我也有一双眼
so do I
我这一双眼怎么会跟你那双眼一样呢？
mine are different than yours
我这双叫做阴阳眼
I have "good-bad" eyes
阴阳眼？
what?
左属阴 ，右属阳
Left is good. Right is bad
蒙上左眼右眼看，蒙上右眼左眼看
stare and I will see
想看就睁大眼，不看就闭上眼
I was born with such eyes
那些鬼是不是很可怕呀？
do ghosts look scary?
鬼本来并不可怕的 ，只不过是人怕鬼
Only if you're afraid of them
其实人也不应该怕鬼
but you have no reason to
为什么？
why?
因为人的身上有三把火
Our bodies have three flames
头顶一把，左肩一把，右肩一把
over our heads and two shoulders
只要火不灭，鬼就不敢靠近
ghosts are afraid of these flames
所以走夜路的时候  你千万不要突然回头
as long as the flames are burning
如果火一灭…
you're safe
你们尿完尿有没有打抖？
do you tremble when you urinate?
有呀
Yes
真的？
really?
真的
Really
这叫做肾亏， 与鬼无关
that has nothing to do with ghosts
是
yes
火一灭就会猛鬼入屋冤鬼缠身
ghosts can possess a man
不过鬼也不是逢人就上身的
not any man thought
是专找那些杀人放火，无恶不作
ghosts only pick bad guys
忘恩负义恩将仇报的人才上身的
like murderers, rapists, traitors
所以俗话说
if you aren't bad
为人不作亏心事，那怕夜半鬼敲门
you shouldn't be afraid of ghosts
开门呀，开门呀
open up
我是眨巴眼
it's piao
快开门 ，快开门呀
let us in
你们一定是做了亏心事  所以才怕成这样
I told you one shouldn't be afraid
快点开门呀
open up
你们干什么？撞邪啦？
did you run into ghosts?
是呀，你怎么知道？
How did you know?
今天早上经过骨坛的时候  我就看见你印堂发黑
I'm an expert in those things
到底发生什么事？
what really happened
就是因为那些骨坛
we passed by a grave
对，对，他向着骨坛尿尿呀
he urinated over it
完了
oh my god
不会吧，我一时贪玩  怎么知道真的有鬼
I didn't mean to insult anyone
邪物立刻就会沿着水往上跑
evil things would flow back with the urine
到了什么地方你自己应该知道
and you should know where to
有没有觉得不舒服？
feel anything?
有点痒痒
A bit itchy
不用娶老婆了 ，玩完了
don't bother to get married
那…你是说
you mean
不会生儿子了
you'll be impotent
贵哥，替他想想办法
is there any remedy?
是呀，你对鬼那么暸解  替他想想办法吧
You're such an expert, help him out
就是嘛
right
办法是没有，只有上炷香拜祭它吧
you'd better deliver some offerings
希望你碰到的不是恶鬼
and pray he's not a bad ghost
那你陪我去吧
can you come with me?
这种事情怎么能够陪你去呢？
You have to go by yourself
有人陪呀就是表示不够诚心  反而更不妙
in order to show you're Sincere
那么明天天一亮我就去
I'll go at dawn then
还要等天亮？
that'd be too late
现在已经到了肚子， 马上就要上脑啦
nothing would cure you
现在又那么害怕
you have to go now
好吧，没办法，那我现在就去
alright, I'll go now
喂喂喂， 多买点东西去拜祭  不要太小器
offer the ghost a lot of good
我知道
sure
先去买两瓶酒，今天晚上有得吃有得看
We have a dinner show tonight
怎么？你是骗他？
you were putting him on?
我是想安定他的心嘛
Just for his peace of mind
眨眼标，你带路，我们马上去
piao, show us the way
还是远点好
That's better
多有得罪，我阿光不懂规矩
Please forgive me
我不是成心的
I didn't mean it
那你是故意的
you did it on purpose
不是不是，我一时贪玩
no, I was just naughty
你很喜欢玩吗？
so you're a naughty boy
那你会不会翻筋斗？
can you do somersaults?
会，会，我翻给你看
Yes, I'll show you
我翻完了
that's it
你知不知道什么叫鬼吃泥呀？
do you know what mud tastes like?
不知道，不知道
No
你抓把泥往嘴里吃吧
Try it and you'll know
不是这些， 是你尿湿了的那些
try the mud you urinated over
味道怎么样？
How's it?
咸咸的
Terrible
以后做人要规矩一点
behave yourself from now on
这顿宵夜真丰富呀
such a wonderful snack
谢谢
thank you
你们这班臭小子
you bastards
回去吃宵夜
let's go home
你别怪我，要怪就怪他
don't blame us, blame him
都是你干的好事
it's all your fault
兄弟 ，撒尿不要紧  可别搞烂我的堂口呀
don't you dare ruining my home
华光沐浴
Bless us please
灵光普照万事兴
Let our show have a good run
左千里眼
enlighten us
看清人情物理
let us see through shams
右顺风耳
guide us
听尽事事非非
lead us away from trouble
须知人生如戏，莫怨戏剧人生
life is just like a show
一切悲欢离合，所有生老病死
all ups and downs
犹如南柯一梦，顿成过眼云烟
they, like dreams, come and go
阿佳，你来替师父开光
chia, perform the rite
朱砂开笔，大吉大利
good luck to us all
开箱大吉
let's celebrate
你们比我可好多了  我是尸骨不全的孤魂野鬼
I'm a wandering ghost
还老让那个恶鬼给欺负  我真是倒霉到家了
that bad ghost bullies me all the time
还不快过来
come over here
惨了惨了 ，那恶鬼的手又发痒了
he's feeling grouchy again
来了
come here
大哥，有什么吩咐？
What can I do for you?
这地方怎么这么脏？
Do you see this mess?
是上…
someone
没话说了吧  这可不是我手痒是你骨头痒
you deserve to be punished
想不打你都不行
you asked for it
这样下去也不是办法
I can't stand this any longer
好，我只有想个法子到阳间避一避
I'd better get back to earth temporarily
各位各位，大家暂时不要工作
hold everything please
不要说我啰苏，我再嘱咐一遍
I have to remind you again
待会祭白虎的时候，千万不要说话
we can't talk during the ceremony
连咳嗽都得忍着
we can't even cough
这两天参汤喝多了 ，嗓子不大舒服
I've been eating too well lately
成天在外面乱泡，小心中马上风
you fool around with women too much
什么时候轮到你多嘴的？
none of your business
我是乱泡又怎么样？你有什么资格？
not anyone can have that privilege
兄弟 ，人不风流只为贫  你是没有那个福气
one has to have money
你也想马上风呀，下辈子嘛
which you don't have
老听人家说你好糗呀，你一定不相信
that was stupid of you
现在相信了
you asked for it
喂，你这是什么兄弟呀？
you're supposed to be a friend
人家这么欺负我  你不但不帮忙还帮着外人来气我
you shouldn't be on his side
要怪只能怪你自己
its all your fault
俗话说宁可得罪君子，莫得罪小人
you shouldn't have messed with bullies
干活去
get to work
哗，煞气好重呀
Ghosts are not welcomed here
怀抱着，幼主爷
Let me save the prince
江山执掌
I'll rule I he country
为什么恨天怨地
don't be mad at heaven
假带惆怅，所谓那般…
I may be sad
无非是哀家假带惆怅
but I won't give up
都只为…
anyway
怀抱着，幼主爷
Let me save the prince
江山执掌…
I'll rule the country
为什么恨天怨地，假带…
don't be mad at heaven
不行，我怕黑的
I'm afraid of the dark
你没事吧？
Are you alright?
原来是你们
It's you guys
大叔，他喝多了两杯
he's drunk
都是你把他灌醉的
it's all your fault
他怎么会醉成这个样子的
you guys are so wild
阿贵，你也太过份了
kuei, I'm disappointed
明天晚上就是你的重头戏  还跟着他们在外边鬼混
tomorrow's a big night for you
还不快点回去睡觉
go home and sleep
回去吧 是
go yes
走
come on
提起宋老三， 两口子卖大烟
I could have danced all night
一辈子没女儿，生了个女蝉娟
取名叫大莲儿，提起大莲儿…
And still I beg for more
女妞真不赖
That was a gorgeous lady
灯怎么会灭了？
What made that happen?
怎么镜子里没有我的影子呢？
Why can't I see myself in the mirror?
使劲呀，顶住呀
Don't fall apart
你可拉住呀，我剪啦
Harder
剪啦
cut it
快上来呀，还有事情做呀
Come back up, I need you
我的头…
My head
出来，快出来呀
Come out
糟糕，事情闹大了
it's getting out of control
快收拾东西
tidy up first
快走
let's go
快，快
hurry
快点
大叔
uncle chiang
你们干什么？
what are you doing?
我们去尿尿
Going to the bathroom
去尿尿
that's right
这几个家伙，不知道在搞什么鬼？
I wonder what they're up to
喂喂，你们昨天晚上把佳大牌给吓晕了
Did you scare chia last nignt?
是呀，他被我们吓得  站也不是坐也不是，只好躺下
We scared the hell out of him
有这么精彩的节目也不通知我
why didn't you let me know?
谁叫你醉得吓死人一样
You were dead drunk
干脆今天晚上再来一次  把他吓得屁滚尿流好不好？
let's do it again tonight
第一次做是天才
to do it once is smart
第二次再做就是蠢才了
twice is stupid
你们这些兔崽子昨晚扮鬼来吓我
you made a fool out of me last night
谁吓你呀，你不要乱说呀
don't be a liar
对不起，我有事先走啦
I have to run
点子是你出的 ， 出了事就想溜呀？
you were the mastermind
现在不打自招
is that right?
佳哥，佳哥…
Chia
佳哥，有话慢慢说吧
Listen to me
说你个屁
like hell I will
别打了
stop it
佳哥
chia
佳哥，和我没关系的 ，佳哥
I wasn't involved
快走，快走
run
不要打了 ，不要打了
stop it
别打了 ，再打我就不客气了
my Patience is running out
不客气？你敢把我怎么样？
that's your problem
不要打了 ，不要打了
stop it
不要打了
你真傻，要抱就抱他
don't just hold me
抱住我让他打？
hold him
不要打，不要打
stop it
住手
hold it
我东西全让给你们打烂了  这怎么办呢？
you ruined my place
你说说看…
come with me
你们是不是疯了？
are you out of your minds?
到这儿来戏还没演就先打起来了
Tonight's our opening night
大叔，我们…
we...
回去再说
Go home
我生来胆小，现在还两腿发软
I'm still in shock
我一害怕就演不出戏来了  你看着办好了
I can't act when I'm in shock
你是他们的老大，居然领着头胡闹
you're supposed to be their guardian
大叔，阿佳还在发脾气
chia's really mad
你们几个实在太不象话
you're really out of line
好了 ，过去跟阿佳道个歉
go apologize to chia
去吧，去吧
go
岂有此理
So out of line
下次发火，他们不光是扮鬼吓我
next time they may not just scare me
弄不好把我房子都给烧了
they may try to kill me
我还要命呢，惹不起我还躲不起
I'd better go away
阿佳别这么说，大人不记小人过
do me a favour, chia
还不道歉
apologize
对不起，佳哥
we're sorry
阿佳，他们都认错了 ，原谅他们吧
forgive them, chia
你们几个听着  向来是别人受我阿佳的气
just remember one thing
你们想作弄我？门儿都没有
I always get even
算了 ，大家出去干活吧
alright, get back to work
这位佳大牌可真神气活现
that chia is an arrogant bastard
快点， 到你了
You're up next
阿佳，等一下就到你了  你跟阿贵先排排戏
can you rehearse with kuei?
排戏？
What?
阿贵艺高人胆大，等一会台上见吧
Kuei doesn't need any rehearsal
阿贵第一次演狮子楼，我怕他不熟习
it's a new role for him
最好跟他练习练习
he needs to block it out
面子是人家给的 ，脸是自己丢的
that's his problem
拜托你告诉他一声叫他用点心  别砸了我的招牌
one shouldn't bite what one can't chew
对不起，我赶着上
I'm sorry
眼睛瞎了？
are you blind?
怎么 ，还没有搞好呀？
You're not ready yet?
你是色盲呀？应该画白色的嘛
Are you color blind?
你黑白都分不黯，大棒槌
That's really stupid
奇怪
weird
你为什么打我？
Why did you hit me?
谁叫你亲我的？
You kissed me
我没亲你呀
I didn't
不是你？难道是鬼吗？
it was a ghost then?
这一次你还想赖皮？
You're going to deny it again?
你说什么？
What?
你怎么乱撞一起， 台上正在做戏呀
Don't mess up the backstage
让一让，对不起让一让
Excuse me
丽姐，逼么急干什么？
what's the rush?
人有三急嘛
Call of nature
对不起，我憋死了
I need to use the bathroom
有好戏看
nice
哗，好棒呀
Wonderful
谁呀？
who's that?
什么？
What?
死鬼眨巴眼，好大的胆子
You peeping Tom
居然敢偷看我小便，不怕长针眼
aren't you ashamed of yourself?
算了 ，算了
Calm down
死标
bastard
阿贵， 到你上场了
kuei, you're up
知道
alright
快点去看阿贵演戏
let me enjoy the show
楼上可是西门庆？
is it hsi upstairs?
正是
Yes
楼下可是武松？
is it wu downstairs?
正是，俺武松来了
Yes, I'm coming up
好呀，好呀
Fantastic
你看贵哥演戏演得多棒呀
kuei's really at it
可不是嘛，才不像阿佳  那小子这么软爬爬的
chia's mind is somewhere else
快到我们了 ，去扮戏吧
we'll be up soon
你怎么这么不小心呀，走路绊倒我
you're so careless, you tripped me
谁绊你了？
I didn't
要你的命
I'llkill you
削头呀
Attack me
快削头呀
attack me
你来真的呀？
are you crazy?
我没有呀
No
起锣鼓啦
Play the drums
他什么时候学会了三个凌空翻的呀？
When did he learn to do that?
好家伙，抢我风头
You're stealing my show
不是呀
I'm not
待会你可杀我了
kill me
杀呀，快点杀呀 我杀不下去
kill me. Come on - I can't
你不杀我怎么下台？
that's how the show ends
想下台那还不容易
I see
怎么杀呀？
what's that?
出漏子
Heaven's sake
武松，你棒，后会有期
I'll see you later
佳哥， 刚才我…
Chia, I was.
王八蛋
Asshol
什么事？什么事？ 别发脾气嘛
- What's wrong? - Chia's mad
不发脾气？  你去问问他他的配角怎么演的？
ask him if he knows his part
我也不知道怎么回事
I don't know how it happened
少说两句 该杀的不杀
shut up - he was
不该演的就拼命表演
improvising selfishly
臭小子，你他妈的整我  你让我以后怎么混呀？
you have ruined my reputation
阿佳，我看他不会的
that must have been an accident
不会？只有你这班主才会请这种人
only you would hire him
不演了 ，换衣服 阿佳
I'm quitting - chia
都是我不好
it's all my fault
凤头大什会来了
The chef's suggestion
贵哥，打都让人打了 ，何必垂头丧气呢
it's not your fault
你不要这样子
don't be so depressed
来来来，喝一杯
come, drink some wine
谁说我垂头丧气？
I'm not depressed
吃面当然低头，难道这样吃的吗？
how else can eat noodles? Like so?
笑什么？
What's so funny?
你们看，说曹操曹操就到
Look at that man over there
伙计，算帐
the check please
吃呀
Eat
干杯
cheers
小伙子，喝这么多的酒迟早跟我一样
drink too much and you'll be like me
举头望明月
Hello, heavenly angel
兔崽子，你也会有这一天的
your turn will come
人家都已经七老八十了  还笑人干什么？
don't make fun of old people
对，要耍人就像贵哥那样，那才叫高招
make fun of mean actor, like what kuei did
贵哥，你好棒  连佳大牌你都敢耍，好样的
you're got guts, making fun of big stars
你们不明白
you don't understand
咱们贵哥也是大牌呀
kuei's a big star too
那家伙太嚣张了  应该杀杀他的威风那才对
chia deserved it anyway
贵哥
kuei
早晚有一天他落在我手里  你们等着瞧我怎样整他
I'll give him hell sooner or later
少嘴硬，你忘了上次  被人骂得你的脸像烧饼一样
last time he gave you hell
说够了没有？一人一句有完没完
have you guys finished?
该听我的吧
Can I speak?
既然你们认为今天晚上我做得对  那么这一顿饭……
I think you guys should buy me dinner
糟了 ，我有事
I've got to run
尿尿呀？
what's wrong?
每次该付帐啦，他就来事了
He uses that trick everytime
贵哥，这次是真的
this time is not a trictk
你以前都是假的是不是？
then you were cheating us before
以前有真有假，不过这次绝对是真的
only once in a while
我槌子放在后堂啦，告辞了
I've got to run
小器鬼
cheap fellow
我们教训教训他
let's teach him a lesson
好，好
good idea
想这么多干什么？得快乐时且快乐
I'd better enjoy myself
快点，快点
hurry
有人来了
someone's coming
你们猜猜眨巴眼回来了没有？
Do you think he's back yet?
他呀没那么快  他连撒尿都比别人慢半拍
No, he's sucn a slow person
是不是和整阿佳那样  拉桌子搬凳子拆柜子的？
should we do what we did to chia?
不用那么麻烦
Not that much trouble
眨巴眼那个笨蛋  随便弄两下子就能把他吓死了
let's make ourselves up as ghosts
我们快去化装吧
get to work right away
好
sure
他们扮鬼吓人真有意思  我也来凑凑热闹
I'm going to join them
你干什么呀你？
What are you doing?
又不是叫你演戏  是叫你扮鬼吓人，笨蛋
Make yourself up as a ghost
我们一人把一边  他跑到那我们在后面吓到那儿好不好？
we'll follow him around
那我呢？
what about me?
你自己看着吧
Improvise
好
okay
你怎么搞的？在他后面吓他
That won't scare him
要让他看得见才有用呀，去
we have to let him see us
咱们这么都没把他吓了
We didn't scare piao
他一个人就把他吓晕了 ，他真棒
but he did it all by himself
一，二，三， 四 ，你是谁呀？
1, 2, 3, 4 who's he?
我是我
It's me
鬼呀
Ghost
真好玩呀
what fun
我一不留神你这个色狼又出去鬼混了
you were fooling around with women
什么？推牌九而已
I was only playing cards
跟三个女人推牌九？
with three women?
赌钱分什么男女，只要有钱输就行了
Women play cards too
那么你是赢还是输呀？
did you win?
输了
No
当然输啦，跟三个女人  推牌九有什么都推光啦
You weren't concentrating on your cards
光就光啦，那是我运气不好
of course I was
你这人的毛病我最清楚了  你快让鬼迷住了
I bet you were hugging those women
白天不讲人，晚上不讲鬼的
don't be ridiculous
鬼呀…
Ghosts
有鬼呀…
ghosts
别人看见鬼，我们跑什么？
why are we running away?
那一定是有鬼了
Someone saw some ghosts
你们看看自己的样子  别人见了当然以为是鬼了
they thought we're ghosts
今天晚上那台戏说不定是鬼来捣乱
a ghost might have ruined our show tonigtht
将军
checkmate
鬼捣乱？我看是他们在捣乱
I think kuei did it on purpose
坐中
watch this
算了 ，别跟那些年青人计较， 早点睡吧
you'd better get some sleep
这盘棋算和了吧
let's call it a draw
和棋？
a draw?
好了 ，好了 ，反正我也没输， 明儿见
It's going to de a draw anyway
对了 ，找个机会你说说阿贵
talk to kuei
怎么说你是半个师父
he always listens to you
再这样下去别怪我不客气
I don't want another sabotage
你看看，你们几个人的德性
Look how druck you are
不是，我们… 阿贵
we - kuei
你先去睡吧，我跟他们说好了
go to bed, I'll talk to them
眼不见为净
spare me
大叔， 刚才我们真的见鬼了
we did run into a ghost
是呀，那个鬼…
right
别说了 ， 先把他救醒了
wake piao up first
照你刚才那个说法，那个鬼…
According to you, that ghost...
阿贵， 先上炷香
Kuei, offer some incense
是
yes
多有得罪
Forgive us
鬼，只不过是人死了以后的幽灵
ghost is the soul of a dead person
当人死了以后  它的灵性凝聚不散，这就叫做鬼
which is supposed to disintegrate upon death
所以鬼跟人一样  仍然保持着他本来的人性
ghosts retain their human nature
鬼也有人性，那照理不会故意害人呀？
they shouldn't hurt us then
是呀，你们遇到的鬼除了吓一跳之外
that ghost didn't hurt you
你们并没有什么损失
did me?
所以我看大概不是恶鬼
So he must not be a bad ghost
鬼也有好坏之分吗？
are there good and bad ghosts?
当然，人也有好人和坏人
Just like there are good and bad men
我知道了 ，好人死了以后变好鬼  坏人死了以后变恶鬼
good men become good ghosts after death
眨巴眼这么好色，死了以后一定是色鬼
piao will become a horny ghost
那么你呢？
what about you?
我？长命百岁
I won't die yet
那就是老鬼
you'll be an old ghost
好了好了 ，你们这班小鬼还不快去睡
you'd better go to bed
不说不害怕 ，越说越害怕
I'm really scared now
我先走了 ， 当心鬼跟着你们 ， 明儿见
don't let any ghosts follow you
大叔， 明儿见
see you tomorrow
等等我
wait for me
大叔，我是孤魂野鬼，我想求你…
I'm a wandering ghost
明天记着把蟒袍熨好
Don't forget to iron my wardrobe
行了行了 ，我会替你熨的 ，快去睡吧
don't worry, get some sleep
你记着呀
don't forget
你别忘了
okay?
你坏了我的事
You'll pay
我要好好的整整你
for messing up my chance
谁撞死我呀？
Who hit me?
当然是有点腾云驾雾
Maybe I'm drunk
板凳也喝醉了
The stool's drunk too
这么坏呀你
naughty
这班孙子又想吓唬我
Must be those idiots again
你这个人真可恶， 让我现原形来吓吓你
I'll let you see me
鬼都不怕？
Tough guy
干什么扮曹操？
stop playing games
吓唬鬼？
who are you?
吓人
A ghost
人吓人
a real one?
鬼吓人
A poltergeist
大法师
I'm an exorcist
你以为我醉了 ，其实我是非常的清醒
I'm not drunk at all
这个王八蛋太可恶了  好，让我到后台去弄坏他的衣箱
I'll mess up his wardrobe chest
是谁把我的衣箱弄乱的？
Who messed up my chest?
说，说，快说？
Speak up
鬼呀，鬼呀
a ghost
又是阿贵
it's kuei again
不是阿贵， 是我呀
I did it
亏你这么大的个子，胆子比妞还小
don't be scared so easily
大白天那儿来的鬼呀，真是…
ghosts don't come out in daytime
你要是不信，你们去吧
you guys go yourselves
我见过鬼，我害怕
I'm scared
慢着
wait
什么事？
what's up?
我一走进戏棚就觉得阴风阵阵  我还是不去了
I'd better not join you guys
你不去了？
are you sure?
你一个人在这里呆着吧
they like loners
等等我
wait for me
早 ，佳哥
hi, chia
早你妈的头
go to hell
干什么？
what's wrong?
别打了
Hold it
有事慢慢说，别打人呀
what's the problem?
扮神扮鬼，扮…
you played ghost
你干什么？
are you crazy?
他发神经的
He's gone nuts
把我的衣箱子都搞乱了
messed up my wardrobe chest
你可别撒赖人呀，我可没动过你的东西
I didn't do it
鬼呀
ghost
我的鸟儿都说是你
my bird saw you played ghost
你们几个狼狈为奸
you're in it together
我打死你
I'll kill you
你们走开，我吃饭的家伙也敢动
Get away from me
你想砸我的饭碗呀？
you're trying to ruin me
你们是那个师父教出来的
shame on your teacher
你骂我什么都可以，那骂我师父就不行
don't you dare criticizing my teacher
不要打了
hold it
打我？大牌你都敢打？
you dared to hit me
别拉我，别拉我…
let go of me
别拦着我
get out of my way
没人拦着他
leave him alone
别拦着我
leave me alone
他呀， 每天晚上到外面鬼混  怪不得脚软了
He fools around with women too much
佳哥，佳哥
chia, chia
阿贵， 发生了什么事
What happened?
他…他…
He...
他怎么变成这个样子？
What happened to him?
还看什么？快点扶起他
Help him up
扶起来呀
Get up.
佳哥
chia
你们走开
leave me alone
我不要你们扶，你们瞧着
I don't need your help
怎么会这个样子的？
what's going on?
你问我，我问谁呀？
How do I know?
千军万马 ，万马千军
Behold my enemies
俺赵子龙，单枪匹马  匹马单枪， 杀出重围
I'm going to kill you all
俺赵云，救幼主 他发疯了
- and save the prince - He's gone nuts
下来，你干什么？
come down
我不但会唱戏，我还会翻筋斗呐
I can do stunts too
马有失蹄
An accident
看什么看？
what are you looking at?
阿佳
Chia
有胡子的是老头儿
my father has a beard
还有你，你长得非常漂亮
you are so pretty
添丁哎落花唉
beautiful dreamers
无顶落雨 阿佳， 阿佳
- beautiful dreamers - Chia, chia
你们看什么？有什么好看的
what are you staring at?
你们再看，我就撞死他，你们没得看
I'll kill myself
快拉住他，快拉住他，你们快拉住他
grab him
不要拉我
let go of me
走
let go
童子尿来了
the baby's here
好脏呀，不要…
that's dirty
我受不了 ， 受不了 ，我走了
I can't stand that
糟糕，糟糕
heaven's sake
哗，这样弄我
wow, do this to me.
他只是撞着鬼， 晕过去了
He was possessed
快扶他到房里去
help him to his room
阿贵，快去找大叔来
kuei, go get uncle chiang
是
sure
我这个主意，你认为怎么样？
What do you think?
好是好，不过要不要  请和尚跟尼姑来给他超度一下
Should we hire some exorcists?
和尚跟尼姑是吃四方的
I don't think so
而我们做戏是吃八方的
exorcists are bad for our business
照我的办法去做，绝无问题
I've got another plan
好，就听你的 ，今天休息一晚上
we'll cancel the show tonight then
我去跟老板商量商量
I'll go arrange that
好
good
你们今天晚上照我话去做
listen to me carefully
威武升堂
court
大叔怎么会做出这种事？
that's not like uncle chiang at all
当是唱戏就行了
he's a good actor too
铁面无私，解尽民间恶案
I represent justice
青天有眼， 了断鬼神奇冤
both on earth and in hell
王朝 ， 马汉
guards
在
yes
镇定一点
be cool
老夫在此，有冤情者  不论是人是鬼，前来申诉
tell the ghosts to present themselves
遵命
yes
包大人在此，不论是人是鬼，前来申诉
do any ghosts have any claims?
上台的时间到了
It's curtain time
不要这么胆小
Have some guts
我不是胆小，根本没胆
I wish I could
可怒，生为人死为鬼，此乃天理
dead men turn into ghosts
既成鬼魅，有冤不诉  反而到阳间作怪，天理不容
but they shouldn't come back to earth
蒙圣上赐尚方宝剑  既可斩阳间刁民泼妇
I'm going to use my sword
更可杀地府的牛鬼蛇神，来人
to drive ghosts back to hell, guards
尚方宝剑在此，小鬼速速前来
ghosts, show yourselves
肃静
be quiet
小鬼在此， 向包大人叩头
Mr. justice
声音是有，怎么没人？
who's that?
你既然在此，还不与老夫现身？
Show yourself
多谢包大人
yes, sir
闭上眼睛
Close your eyes
有何冤情，快些诉说
what's your problem?
回禀大人，小鬼乃潮州人氏  乱刀斩死，尸分七段
I was slashed to death
但杀死小鬼的仇家  已经法网难逃，被处斩而死
the murderer was caught and executed
这都是三百年前的事了
that was 300 years ago
既然如此，为何前来申诉？
then what's your problem?
禀大人， 因为小鬼无人超度  变成孤魂野鬼了
But I've become a wandering ghost
求大人把我的尸骨收集齐全， 另藏地方
please collect my bones and bury them
让我安安乐乐的去投胎做人
to make way for my reincarnation
听来言之有理，老夫就依你所求
all right, I'll help you
多谢大人
thank you
小鬼听命
listen
在
yes
今后不准再到阳间滋扰众生
don't come to earth again
如有食言，定斩不赦
or I'll terminate you
小鬼感恩不尽，怎敢还到阳间闹事呀
I'm not an ungrateful ghost
谅你不敢
that's good
大人答应你了  你尸骨在那里快说出来吧
tell us where your bones are
大人，就埋在小鬼的脚下
right underneath this stage
但是戏台之下有两…
but there are two
什么玩意呀？
what's going on?
你们太离谱了  今天不开锣也不告诉我一声
Nobody told me the show was cancelled
干什么干什么？穿蟒袍子干什么？
why are you in wardrobe?
阿佳
Chia
你就不是大叔吗？你还扮包公干什么？
aren't you uncle chiang?
年纪大把了 ，还这么大的戏瘾呀
Are you too fond of acting?
阿佳，你听我说
Listen to me
说什么？
what?
你以为你真的是包公  来吓唬我呀，你发神经病
Who do you think you are?
你穿的不是我的蟒袍吗？  快把它脱下来还给我
You're wearing my wardrobe. Take it off
不要嘈，别以为你是大牌就目中无人
don't be an arrogant bastard
兄弟不和又被鬼耍
you were possessed
显然你已经到了人憎鬼厌的地步了
that shows ghosts dislike you
你今天被鬼缠身， 自己撞柱子撞伤了头
you were possessed today
你的这班兄弟于心不忍  所以不避吉不避凶
we all felt sorry for you
为了你，他们和我一起扮包公审鬼
so we decided to tame the ghost
希望能够替你消灾解难
so that you can be saved
反而你是非不分，以怨报德
but you're so ungrateful
你今天早上就让那个上身了
the ghost made a fool of you today
还有，你的衣箱也是被那个鬼给搞乱的
he also messed up your chest
你说说看，我跟了这么久  有没有跟你开过玩笑？
you've known me long enough
做过什么糊涂事？
have I ever lied?
大叔，对不起
Forgive me
阿佳，你明白就好
I'm glad you understand
大叔，现在怎么办？
what should we do now?
那个鬼说他的骨头在戏台底下
The ghost's bones are right underneath
好， 马上去挖
let's start digging
喂， 喂，快过来看看
Come over here
千万别弄碎了 ，小心点
be easy with them
大叔， 骨头全都挖出来了
We've found all the bones
找个风水好的地方埋起来
bury them in a nice place
是
sure
潮州大兄，你的骨头我们替你埋好了
We've buried your bones
以后你就用不着再做孤魂野鬼了
you won't be wandering anymore
保佑我们戏班场场满座，财源广进
bless us and our show
潮州大兄，今天天不亮  我就和爱姐起来做鱼丸孝敬你
I've brought you some food
是呀，希望你喜欢
I hope you'll like it
他是潮州人，一定喜欢吃鱼丸的
I'm sure he'll like it
我也上一炷香
I'll offer some incense
我来
let me
你们看，他老爹死他也没这么孝顺
he looks very Sincere
当然，他怕潮州大兄再来缠住他
he's afraid of being possessed again
要是真缠住你就算多烧点冥钱也没用呀
ghosts don't give up that easily
那当然了
that's true
潮州大兄，希望你有机会  早日投胎从新做人
good luck to your reincarnation
叫他快娶个老婆  让潮州大兄投胎当他儿子不就行了
let him reincarnate as your son
眨巴眼，说话不要太损人
don't be nasty, piao
佳哥，我来帮你烧几张
let me help you, chia
潮州大兄，千万保佑
dear ghost
其实佳哥人不错的 ，又肯热心教人
chia's a very good teacher
假如你喜欢学戏，有空可以跟他学学
you should come study with him
好了好了 ，我们拜完了 ， 回去吧
all right, let's go home
走吧
come on
阿贵，真是不好意思  以前的事不要放在心里边
I want to apologize for my past behavior
不会的 ，我全忘了
let bygones he bygones
喂喂，他想跟我们蹭一块儿
he wants to be our friend
怎么会呀，他会跟我们握手呀？
he won't shake our hands
他是看人的 ，走吧
he's too proud
阿光，真不好意思，以前是我不对
I was wrong before
对不起
I'm sorry
大家和气多好
we're all friends
不好意思
I'm sorry
走，走
let's go
改天我请你们吃饭
I'll buy you dinner
别客气
don't go overboard
这么大的场面
Such a big occasion
大家这么辛苦吃顿便饭嘛，请随便
thank you for all your help
菜洗好了没有？
Are the vegetables ready?
好，洗好了洗好了
Sure
丽姐，想不到你烧菜有两下子
I didn't know you're such a good cook
快干活吧，不然就来不及了
get on with the work
把盘子洗干净
wash the plates
好，洗盘子
okay
你撞见鬼啦？
are you nuts?
是你撞我嘛
You hit me
丽姐，有什么让我帮忙的吗？
Can I be of any help?
阿贵，今天可真是稀奇了
Kuei, that's strange
堂堂大牌名角 ，居然肯到厨房来帮忙
a star helps out in the kitchen
丽姐，你别说笑话了
stop teasing me
帮我宰了这只甲鱼
kill this thing for me
别动
don't move
你把它揪出来，我来按住它
I'll hold it, you pluck it out
又揪又按，揪那儿呀？
pluck what out?
揪头呀，我按住了
Its head
佳哥， 丽姐揪王八头本事大了
she's very good at these things
揪你的头，揪出来
pluck it out
丽姐，一刀下去不就一头血
that'd be very bloody
宰王八当然是一头血，丽姐，对吗？
of course it'd be bloody
贫嘴，宰呀
just chop it off
真的宰吗？
for real?
宰呀，宰呀
Do it
大哥，请上座
please sit down
各位，请入席吧
make yourselves at home
大叔，喝一杯
Cheers
喝一杯
cheers
各位，静一静
attention please
各位兄弟姐妹，今天不用开锣
we're not working tonight
大家尽管多喝几杯，喝醉了也没有关系
so don't worry about getting drunk
谢谢，谢谢
Thank you
够了 ，够了
I've to quit
大叔，这鱼很新鲜呀
this fish is delicious
这鱼很新鲜
it's delicious
阿丽怎么没有出来呀
where's our leading lady?
在厨房盛甲鱼汤
She's preparing the soup
大叔，我敬你一杯
Cheers, uncle chiang
应该敬的 ，这次全靠大叔  扮包公才消灾解难
you took care of the ghost
你也帮了忙
you helped out too
佳哥，你现在没事了
chia, you can relax now
你知不知道你鬼上身的时候  是什么德性？
do you know what you looked like?
那我怎么会知道呢
No, I don't
让我学给你看看
I'll show you
看看， 是这样的
you were like this
你说像不像呀
what do you say?
他学得真像，快过来吃东西吧
Knock it off, come and eat
还不过来
come on
怎么会这样的？
what happened?
眨眼标，你的演技未免太过火了
Don't overdo it
喂， 喂，吃鱼呀
have some fish
你搞得桌面都哆嗦了 ，坐下吧
Don't shake the table
你抽筋了
you've got a cramp?
我帮你夹
I'll help you
怎么回事？
What's wrong?
死了
He's dead
死了人了
he's dead
静一静
Be quiet
散开
Spread out
快走
Run
大叔，大叔，你没事吧
are you all right?
我没事
I'm fine
大家散开，快点散开，散开…
Spread out quickly
散开…
spread out
快走，快走，快点走
run
大叔
Uncle chiang
快救人呀，救人呀
help
你这个恶鬼
You stupid ghost
贵哥
kuei
阿贵
不要去呀
don't go
贵哥… 阿贵
kuei - kuei
贵哥
kuei
别这样
don't
贵哥…
Kuei
别冲动
galm down
阿贵呢？
Where's kuei?
无情鬼
Ungrateful
轻一点，轻一点
Easy
阿贵， 刚才你那儿去了？
Where did you go?
我把那恶鬼的骨头全部挖出来砸烂
I smashed every bone of that ghost
你为什么要这样做？
why did you do that?
为什么？谁叫他不知好歹  恩将仇报把我们兄弟弄得这么惨
He's ungrateful and he almost killed us
你说鬼有鬼性
we were nice to him
大叔，原来鬼性就是  忘恩负义，以怨报德
but obviously he's a bad ghost
照理他不会这样对付我们
I don't think he did it
难道我还冤枉了他？
who else?
你这个恶鬼有种就  现出原形来，一个对一个
Show yourself if you've got guts
我要把你打下十八层地狱，永不超生
I want to drive you to hell
走开
move over
对啦，你的骨头是我砸的 ，怎么样呀？
I smashed your bones. So?
你是个恶鬼，臭鬼，烂鬼…
You're a bad ghost
忘恩负义鬼
you're ungrateful
阿贵，冷静一点
calm down
你们说我什么都可以  说我忘恩负义就可不行
I'm not an ungrateful ghost
我这个人呀，不  我这个鬼生平最恨人家说我没义气
I resent people calling me one
你就是没义气
but you're ungrateful
阿贵哥，你们根本就没有  把我的骨头挖出来呀
you didn't dig out my bones
哎呀，你还在那儿说瞎话
you really are unreasonable
那个骨头是我的
whose bones were those?
我问你，那天晚上我们扮包公来审你
You begged us to bury your bones
对呀
right
你自己说你的骨头埋在戏台底下
your bones were underneath the stage
话是不错，可惜台下边有两副骨头
but there were two sets of bones
两副骨头？
two sets?
没错呀
That's right
要不要上香拜祭它？
we digged out the wrong set
拜祭也没有用了 ， 它还会来找你们的
that's why he's mad at you
什么？还要来耍我们？
will he come again?
不是耍是要你的命
Yes, to kill you
把我们害得这么惨还不够？
he's brought hell to us already
本来还不至于  谁叫阿贵砸了人家的骨头
but kuei smashed his bones afterwards
还让狗叼走一块，让他尸骨不全
he has to come for revenge
当然非跟你们拼命不可
he's determined
那我们怎么办？
what can we do?
我不知道，你们自己想办法吧
I don't know
天一黑它就要来了
he'll come tonight
光天化日我亦不能久留 ，我走了
I've got to run now
你们自己想办法吧
good luck
你别走呀，你别走呀
don't leave us
都是我不好
it's all my fault
大叔，我们离开这里吧
let's leave this town
走是走不了啦
he'll follow us
那怎么办呢？
what should we do?
来， 马上准备一大桶黑狗血和几捆绳子
Get some dog blood and nets
绳子用黑狗血染红
stain the nets with the blood
织成大网 ，挂在戏棚的四面
hang them around the theatre
然后把黑狗血洒遍戏棚的地板  等待恶鬼到来
and splash the floor with the blood
当那个恶鬼给网网住，立刻把棚顶打开
When the ghost falls into a net
阳光照着恶鬼， 它就劫数难逃了
open the roof up and let sunlignt in
我们扮钟馗捉鬼
We'll play exorcists
狗血网？
Blood nets?
钟馗？
An exorcist?
它怕了 ，拿酒来
Bring the wine
抓住它
Grab him
用狗血淋它
Splash him with blood
是
right
接着
catch
包围它
Surround him
往那里走？
You're dead
网住它
Use the nets
拿狗血来
Bring the blood
糟了 ，着火了
A fire
还站着干什么？
don't just stand there
快点弄灭它呀
put it out
原来是假的
Actors only
大叔，大叔…
Uncle chiang
小心呀
Be careful
大叔
Uncle chiang
多谢祖师爷显灵
Thanks to our guardian angel